<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nonconformity not inconsistent with loyality, or, Protestant-dissenters no seditious or disloyal sectaries evidenc'd in a sober discourse upon those statutes, by which the Protestant-dissenters are prosecuted at this day : humbly offered to the candid consideration of all Protestants, whether conformists or nonconformists / by James Jones ...</title>
            <author>Jones, James, fl. 1683-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J958</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17214</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12394975</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12394975</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61106</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61106)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 920:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nonconformity not inconsistent with loyality, or, Protestant-dissenters no seditious or disloyal sectaries evidenc'd in a sober discourse upon those statutes, by which the Protestant-dissenters are prosecuted at this day : humbly offered to the candid consideration of all Protestants, whether conformists or nonconformists / by James Jones ...</title>
                  <author>Jones, James, fl. 1683-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by William Bateman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61106:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NONCONFORMITY <hi>Not Inconſiſtent</hi> WITH LOYALTY: OR, Proteſtant-Diſſenters NO SEDITIOUS OR DISLOYAL SECTARIES: EVIDENC'D IN A SOBER DISCOURSE upon thoſe STA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TUTES, by which the Proteſtant-Diſſenters are Proſecuted at this Day. Humbly offered to the Candid Conſideration of all Proteſtants, whether Conformiſts or Nonconformiſts.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JAMES JONES,</hi> a Proteſtant-Diſſenter, and now a Priſoner in <hi>Wood-Street-Compter</hi> for Nonconformity.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſther. 3.8, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And <hi>Haman</hi> ſaid unto King <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> There is a Certain People Scattered abroad, and Diſperſed among the People, in all the Provinces of thy Kingdom, and their Laws are divers from all the People, neither keep they the Kings Laws; Therefore it is not for the Kings profit to ſuffer them: If it pleaſe the King, let it be written, That they may be Deſtroyed.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 42.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>But this is a People robbed and ſpoiled, they are all of them ſnared in holes, and they are hid in Priſon-Houſes: They are for a Prey, and none delivereth; and for a Spoil, and none ſaith, Reſtore.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be Sold by <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Bateman,</hi> and moſt Bookſellers. 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:61106:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61106:2"/>
            <head>To all Sincere Proteſtants, whether they be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, or Nonconformiſts.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Fellow Proteſtants,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Do humbly preſent to your ſober conſideration, a Brief Diſcourſe concerning ſeveral Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes by which they Proteſtant Diſſenters are Proſecuted, to the very great dammage of multitudes of Families, who are his Majeſties Faithful Subjects, and can Appeal to God and the King, that they are perſons of <hi>Loyalty,</hi> notwithſtanding their <hi>Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity.</hi> And as it is Recorded concerning Holy <hi>Daniel,</hi> who was the great Nonconformiſt of that day, <hi>Dan. 6.5.</hi> That <hi>he could not be fairly accuſed of any matters to make him a criminal, except it were concerning the Law of his God;</hi> Even ſo it may be truly ſaid of the Nonconformiſts in <hi>England,</hi> however they may be Reproached and be ſpattered as a Seditious and Rebellious People. But it is well known, that it is no new thing for ſuch as fear God, and are greatly favoured by God, to be miſcalled. <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which was <hi>the City of the Great King, viz.</hi> God, the King of Kings, <hi>Mat. 5.35;</hi> was called <hi>the Rebellious and Bad City, Ezra 4.12.</hi> and in verſe <hi>19. A City of Inſurrection, Rebellion and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi> And Jeſus Chriſt was charged with Blaſphemy, <hi>Mat. 26.56.</hi> and called <hi>a Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Mat. 27.63.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was called <hi>a Poſtilent Fellow, a Mover of Sedition, and a Ring-leader of the Sect of the Nazareens, Acts 24.5.</hi> and his way of Worſhip was called Hereſie, <hi>verſe 14.</hi> And no marvel if it be ſo in thoſe our days. But now it will be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by ſome, that the Proteſtant Diſſenters are in a Conſpiracy and Bloody Plot againſt the Kings Perſon and Government.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto which let this anſwer be Conſidered:</p>
            <p>That although ſome particular perſons that have been counted Diſſenters, may be ſo wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned, yet that is no proof that this is the <hi>Diſſenters Plot,</hi> no more then, (becauſe ſome of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> may be proved to have been in ſuch a Conſpiracy) it can be called the <hi>Church of England's Plot;</hi> which to affirm would be very wicked and abominable; for it would render the Church-Proteſtants no better than Traytors.</p>
            <p>However, if either any of the Diſſenters, or of the Church-men, ſhould be ſo wicked as to be really guilty, let them ſuffer the Juſtice of the Law, that others may bear, and fear, and do no more ſo wickedly. But God forbid that a whole Party of any ſort of People ſhould be charged with the wickedneſs of ſome of the ſame Party: <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> were guilty of a horrid and Bloody Fact, in cutting off <hi>Hamor</hi> and <hi>Shechem,</hi> which was the Prince of that Land, and his Son, and they alſo cut off the Inhabitants of that City where they Ruled, becauſe that <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem</hi> the Son of <hi>Hamor,</hi> had defiled <hi>Jacobs</hi> Daughter. See the whole Story in <hi>Gen. 34.</hi> But it would be a very unrighteous thing to charge good old <hi>Jacob</hi> with this Bloody Crime, becauſe he it as their Father; or to charge the reſt of his Sons, becauſe they were <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi's</hi> Brethren. It is enough, that they who be really guilty of any Crimes, be charged with them, and be Proſecuted ſo as to ſuffer justly for them.</p>
            <p>And beſides this, it muſt be conſidered that ſuch as have been innocent perſons have been Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of high Crimes, and have ſuffered death; as for instance, <hi>Naboth</hi> was accuſed that he had <hi>Blaſphemed God and the King,</hi> and was ſtoned to death for it; when indeed it was a Plot invented by <hi>Jezebel,</hi> and managed by the Elders of the City where <hi>Naboth</hi> dwelt. <hi>See 1</hi> Kings <hi>21. v. 9, 10, 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we find it concerning our Bleſſed Saviour, he was Accuſed that he ſaid, <hi>he would deſtroy the Temple, which was made with hands, and within three days build another without hands,</hi> Mark <hi>14.58.</hi> Now Chriſt had ſpoke of Deſtroying and Raiſing of a Temple in three days, ſee <hi>John 2. v. 19. Jeſus anſwered and ſaid unto them, Deſtroy this Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and in three days I will raiſe it up,</hi> v. <hi>21. But he ſpoke of the Temple of his Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we have two famous Inſtances of falſe Accuſations concerning words; <hi>Naboth</hi> was Accuſed of words that he <hi>never ſpoke;</hi> Chriſt was Accuſed of ſome words <hi>he had ſpoke,</hi> but the Accuſation was not <hi>juſt as the words were ſpoken:</hi> for though he ſpoke of a Temple, and deſtroying of it, and raiſing of it, he did not ſay the Temple that was made with hands, neither did he ſay that he himſelf would deſtroy any Temple, but he ſpoke to the <hi>Jews,</hi> who he knew would deſtroy his Body, and ſaid to them, <hi>Deſtroy this Temple,</hi> and as for Raiſing of it up, that he ſaid ſhould be his own work; <hi>And I will Raiſe it up in three days.</hi> But he was Proſecuted for ſaying he would deſtroy the Temple of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and build it in three days, when it was no ſuch thing. And in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Chronicle, it is ſtoired of a good Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper
<pb facs="tcp:61106:3"/>or, (in the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth) that told his Son, who was a Child, ſaying, <hi>Thou art Heir to the Crown,</hi> meaning his houſe, which was the ſign of the <hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>Cheap-ſide.</hi> But the Honeſt Citizen was Accuſed of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and ſuffered Death as a Traytor. <hi>See bakers Chron.</hi> However, it muſt be confest that Trayterous Deſigns have been too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times managed againſt the Kings of ſeveral Kingdoms, and againſt the King of <hi>England</hi> in particular; and whoſoever can be proved really guilty thereof, ought to ſuffer according to their Crimes.</p>
            <p>But as for my own part, who do profeſs my ſelf a Proteſtant Diſſenter, <hi>I</hi> do ſolemnly profeſs, before Almighty God, that <hi>I</hi> do with my Soul, abhor all acts of violence to the meanest of the Kings Subjects; and do deem it <hi>ten thouſand times worſe to offer any violence to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Kings Majeſty: 1.</hi> Becauſe of the Greatneſs of his Perſon, he being by the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God the Head of the Nation: <hi>2.</hi> Becauſe the ſhedding of his Blood, and taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of his Life, is the ready way to make the Kingdom ſwim in Blood, by reaſon of theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions that would attend ſuch a bloody action. Beſides the greatneſs of the Sin in the ſight of that God who will make inquiſition for Blood.</p>
            <p>And therefore though perſons of contrary minds to the Government in matters of Religion, may be greatly oppreſſed becauſe of Laws made againſt them, yet it is their duty to walk by theſe Following Rules.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1. To be ſubject to the Higher Powers,</hi> Rom. <hi>13.1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2. To Render to all their Dues,</hi> viz. <hi>Tribute, Cuſtom, Fear and Honour,</hi> Rom <hi>13.7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3. To be patient in Tribulation,</hi> Rom. <hi>12.12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4. To Recompence to no man Evil for Evil,</hi> Rom. <hi>12.17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5. To Pray for them that Perſecute them and deſpitefully uſe them,</hi> Mat. <hi>5.44.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6. If it be poſſible as much as in them lieth, to live peaceably with all men,</hi> Rom. <hi>12.11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7. Not to be overcome of Evil, but to overcome Evil with Good,</hi> Rom. <hi>12.21.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <closer>
               <signed>JAMES JONES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>A Table of the Principal Things contained in this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> OF Government in General, <hi>Page 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> OF the Government of <hi>England</hi> in particular, <hi>Page 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> An Anſwer to thoſe that object againſt the Proteſtant Diſſenters, becauſe <hi>Venners</hi> Inſurrection, <hi>Page 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> A Diſcourſe upon the Statute of <hi>1 Eliz. 2.</hi> concerning the Penalty of Twelve-pence for not coming to ſome Church or Chappel to hear Common-Prayer every Sunday and Holy-day, <hi>P. 4, 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> A Diſcourſe upon the Statute of <hi>23. Eliz.</hi> concerning the Penalty of Twenty Pounds a Month, for not Repairing to ſome Church or Chappel, or uſual Place of Common-Prayer, <hi>p. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> A Diſcourſe upon the Statute of <hi>29. Eliz.</hi> and the third of King <hi>James,</hi> concerning the ſame Offence. <hi>page 7, 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> A Diſcourſe of the Statute of the 35th of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> commonly called the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration Act. <hi>page 9, 10, 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> A Diſcourſe upon the Oath of Allegiance. <hi>page 12, 13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> The Oath of Allegiance it ſelf, and King <hi>James</hi> his Expoſition of it. <hi>page 14, 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> The Oath of Supremacy, and Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Expoſition of it, and the Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Confirming the ſaid Queens Expoſition. <hi>page 15, 16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> The Statute of <hi>17. Car. 2.</hi> chap. <hi>2.</hi> conſidered, Intituled, <hi>An Act for Reſtraining Nonconformiſts from Inhabiting Corporations,</hi> commonly called the <hi>Five-Mile Act, page 16, 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Conſiderations upon the Statute of <hi>22. Car. 2.</hi> chap. <hi>1.</hi> Intituled, <hi>An Act to ſuppreſs Seditious Conventicles, &amp;c. Page 17, 18, 19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> An Acoount of the Proceedings of the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, for not coming to Church, and Receiving the Sacrament, <hi>Page 19. 20.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> The ſeveral ways of obtaining Abſolution from the Sentence of Excommunication. Ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> Reaſons why Proteſtant Diſſenters cannot Conform. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> The Concluſion. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61106:3"/>
            <head>NONCONFORMITY <hi>Not Inconſiſtent</hi> WITH LOYALTY: OR, <hi>Proteſtant-Diſſenters no Seditious or Diſloyal Sectaries.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Evidenc'd in A Sober Diſcourſe upon all thoſe Statutes by which the Proteſtant-Diſſenters are Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted at this Day.</head>
            <p n="1">I. <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Overnment in Nations and Kingdoms is the Glory of this World, for thereby things of all ſorts, and Perſons of all Degrees, are Regularly managed and diſpoſed of; and though ſome Governments are far better then others, yet that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment that is not ſo good as it ought to be, is far better then no Government at all; for without Government there is nothing but dreadful Confuſion, each party ſtriving to have his own Luſt a Law for others; Therefore it is far better for Common Good to be under a Government by ſetled Laws, though in ſome things bad, then to be under the Will and Pleaſure of any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſon, or any Number of Perſons, whoſe Proceedings may be according to that Power and Might in a way of force, as they are able to Exerciſe over each other; and ſo, as there may be an Uncertainty of Commanding, there muſt needs be an Uncertainty of Obeying, and ſo an Uncertainty of any Safety.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Government of Nations doth very much differ from each other in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular forms thereof, ſome being governed by Kings, and ſome by States, and ſome by other Governours; but tho there is a Difference in forms of Government, and in the Titles of Governours, yet they all agree in the Subſtantials of Government, <hi>viz.</hi> To maintain a Publick Peace amongſt themſelves, and to be ſo United unto each other, as to defend themſelves againſt Forreign Foes, and to puniſh ſuch as are Offenders, in offering any kind of Violence to the Perſons, or Power of their Governours, or to the Perſons, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and Properties of each other. And in theſe and ſuch like things, thoſe that differ in matters of Religion, from what may be the Eſtabliſhed Worſhip of the Countrey where they are Inhabitants, yet they ought to behave themſelves in all peaceable manner with Subjection to thoſe that are in Authority; For the People of God in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61106:4"/>Times, though in Religious matters they differ'd from thoſe Countreys where they were Inhabitants, yet they were taught by the Doctrine of the Apoſtles to maintain the Welfare and Grandure of the Government. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Render therefore to all their Dues, Tribute to whom Tribute is due, Cuſtom to whom Cuſtom, Fear to whom Fear, Honour to whom Honour; And alſo to lead a quiet and peaceable Life in all Godlineſs, and Honeſty under Authority;</hi> ſee 1 Tim. 2.2.</p>
            <p n="3">III. And it may be truly ſaid that <hi>England</hi> is moſt happy in its Government, as it conſiſteth of King, Lords and Commons, by whom Laws are made for the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; And the Law-makers are alſo under the Power of the Laws they make. And this is moſt excellent, that each Party of the Law-makers, conſidered as King, Lords and Commons, cannot impoſe any thing as a Law upon the Subjects in General, nor upon each other, without a mutual Conſent, <hi>viz.</hi> The King cannot impoſe a Law upon the Peers; The Peers cannot impoſe a Law upon the King; The King and Peers cannot impoſe a Law upon the Commons; The Commons cannot impoſe a Law upon the King and Peers; but King Peers and Commons by a joint Conſent do make Laws.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. And each Party who have matters one againſt another, cannot Determine or Iſſue their Caſe according to their own Minds and Wills, and at their own Pleaſures, but the Determination of all matters muſt be in a Legal Way, being tryed before the Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Judges of the Realm, who are Required by Law that they ſhall not deny nor delay Juſtice; &amp; the whole Iſſue of matters in Controverſy muſt be determined by a Jury of the Neighbourhood, <hi>viz.</hi> Twelve men of Honeſty and Wiſdom, that ſo the Kings Subjects may receive no Wrong by Knaves or Fools; and in ſome great Criminal Caſes, the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner or Accuſed Party is allowed by Law to except againſt a great Number of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who are Summoned to be of his Jury, without ſhewing any Reaſon, but only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he doth not like them; and may after that Number is Expired, except againſt many others upon ſuch Reaſons as the Court can juſtly approve of. So tender is the Law of mens Lives, that good Proviſion is made for the Right Adminiſtration of Juſtice; that ſo the Innocent may be acquitted, and none but the Guilty may be puniſhed; unleſs the King extend Mercy in Pardonable Caſes, in hope of the Offenders Amendment.</p>
            <p n="5">V. And this further muſt be conſidered, that one part of the Law-makers are the Houſe of Commons, who are Choſen by the People, and have power to prepare Bills for the Conſent of the Houſe of Lords, and alſo to Accept or Reject Bills from the Houſe of Lords, before they are Preſented to his Majeſty for his Royal Aſſent; and therefore if any Laws be made that are not for the peoples profit, the Electors of ſuch Members of Parliament muſt Reflect upon themſelves for making ſuch a Choice, and look better to their Choice for the time to come.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. And ſometimes His Majeſties Leige People may Receive and Suſtain Damages and Wrongs, not becauſe the Laws are bad, but becauſe it is badly managed by ſuch as do not well underſtand the Laws; or elſe becauſe they may have ſome Antipathy in their minds againſt thoſe that are Proſecuted; and ſo, that they may Accompliſh their own wills againſt ſome particular perſons, do ſometimes venture to ſwerve from the true meaning of the Law.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. And for the good of the King and Kingdom, the Wiſdom of the Nation Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament doth ſometimes upon mature conſideration prepare Bills for Acts of Parliament, in which ſome former Laws are Confirmed and Explained, and ſome Laws are Repealed, and ſome New Laws are made.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Now therefore that Juſtice may be Rightly Adminiſtred unto all the Kings Subjects, it doth highly concern all Mayors of Cities and of other Corporations, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61106:4"/>all Juſtices of the Peace in the ſeveral Counties of this Realm, together with all other-Peace-Officers concerned in the Executing of the Laws, To make ſure of a Right Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of their ſeveral Offices according to Law, that as they may not come ſhort, ſo they may not go beyond that power the Law hath committed unto them, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come needleſs Proſecuters and Troublers of the Kings Subjects to their ſhurt and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; though after great Charge and Expence, ſuch may be Releived by the Kings Honourable Judges, and it may be, thoſe that were their Troublers may pay for it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to their Coſt and ſhame, when Juſtice ſhineth in the Kings Courts of Juſtice, being diſplayed impartially between the King and his Subjects, and alſo between Subject and Subject.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. In the Right Adminiſtration of Juſtice, it doth highly concern the Executors of the Laws, to conſider the Nature of the Offences puniſhable by the Law, whether they be great or ſmall, whether they be ſuch as are any way a hurt to the perſon of the King, or to the Publick Peace of the Kingdom, or whether they be ſuch things as tho' the Law doth count Offences yet in themſelves are not maters at all Criminal, <hi>viz.</hi> matters of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, by reaſon of mens Differing Opinions in matters of Religion, which in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are no way hurtful to any mans Perſon, Name or Eſtate.</p>
            <p n="10">X. It is alſo to be ſoberly conſidered, what kind of perſons the Deemed and Reputed Offenders are, whether they do at all own and adhere to any Forreign Jurisdiction, or whether they do own and approve of the Kings Majeſty as the Supream Governour of this Realm, and all other his Dominions and Countries, in oppoſition to the Pope, and all foreign Jurisdiction; who though they may in ſome things of Religion differ from ſome matters of Worſhip as Eſtabliſhed by Law, are yet known to be ſuch as fear God and Honour the King, and profeſs, practice, and promote the Proteſtant Religion, and are ready to aſſiſt and maintain the Government in the Peace and Tranquility of it, both with Perſon and Purſe, as hath been demonſtrated by the Proteſtant Diſſenters in general; and that in a time and times of great Diſtreſs; when they have been ſeverely Proſecuted in City and Country, to the very great dammage of many good Families, who deſire to live and dye his Majeſties Peaceable Subject.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will object and ſay, That the Diſſenters have been Troublers and Diſturbers of the Government, and ſo call to Remembrance the Inſurrection that was made by <hi>Venner</hi> and his Party in the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto which a ſatisfactory anſwer may be returned, and therefore pray let theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing things be conſidered in the behalf of the generality of the Proteſtant Diſſenters.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Inſurrection of <hi>Venners</hi> Party was condemned by the Diſſenters through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Kingdom, as an Act of great violence and wickedneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Conſpiracy was but by a few, <hi>viz.</hi> 29. who were known to be men of fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Spirits and ſwimming Brains, and would fain have been at the ſame work in the time of <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> if he had not very timely prevented it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though they were Diſſenters, yet it is well known, that they were fierce-ſpirited men againſt all other Diſſenters that were not of their deſperate minds.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Law hath taken hold of them, and their perſons have been puniſhed ſeverely for that deſperate practice, and the Diſſenters in general throughout this Realm were not concerned in that Buſineſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is not at all fair, that any Party of men ſhould be charged with, and condemned for the fooliſh raſh Proceedings of ſome that may be called by the ſame diſtinguiſhing name; for ſuppoſe ſome Presbyterians, ſome Independants, ſome Anabaptiſts, and ſome Quakers, ſhould Conſpire againſt the Government, it will not be fair dealing to deem that all of thoſe names are all alike in ſuch bad things.</p>
            <p>For by this Rule, all <hi>French-men, Scotch-men, Iriſh-men,</hi> and other Countries muſt be deemed Enemies to the Government, becauſe ſome have been proved to be ſo; yea according to the aforeſaid Rule, all ſorts of Tradeſmen, Gentlemen, Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61106:5"/>Knights, Lords, Earls, Dukes, though good Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> muſt be cenſured and feared to be Traytors, becauſe ſome of ſuch degrees and qualities have been proved to be ſuch Criminals; but as this is far from Chriſtianity, ſo it is very far from good humanity: it is enough that thoſe and only thoſe who are the Criminals be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to their Crimes, and as for all others who are not concerned in ſuch Crimes, tho they be under the ſame Denomination Reſpecting Degrees in the World, or in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, yet they ought to be eſteemed and favoured as Loyal Subjects to the King, although there may be ſome matters of Religion that the Law doth account Offences.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. That Juſtice may be Rightly Adminiſtred, and Oppreſſion may be avoided, the nature and weight of the puniſhments inflicted by Law, ought to be well conſidered, and compared with the Offences, eſpecially if there be ſeveral ways of puniſhment for one and the ſame Offence; and if the Executors of the Law, be left at liberty to take which way they pleaſe, of the greater or ſmaller puniſhments: For as much as it ſavoreth too much or Severity, if not Cruelty, for ſuch as profeſs Chriſtianity, to proceed violently one againſt another, when they may be more gentle and friendly to each other, eſpecially in matters of Conſcience, but it is to be lamented, that too many perſons, partly for want of Underſtanding in the Law, and partly by reaſon of violent ſpirits, inſtead of being Legal and Merciful Proſecutors, are dreadful Oppreſſors &amp; Perſecutors of ſuch as are their Fellow Proteſtants.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. Now for as much as the poor Proteſtant Diſſenters are Proſecuted and ſo are diſtreſſed by divers Laws that are put in Execution againſt them; let thoſe Laws be ſoberly conſidered, together with the perſons and things for which they are Proſecuted, that ſo neither the Laws nor the Kings Subjects may be abuſed by reaſon of the inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Proceedings of thoſe that have not ſuch a good Underſtanding of the Laws as they ought to have, for the well managing of that Office or Authority they have arrived unto. And beſides ſuch ignorance in the Law, men in Authority are ſometimes attended with ſuch diſpleaſure of mind, as may be called ill-will, againſt ſome perſons that they may be concerned with, in the exerciſe of ſuch Authority; and ſo are apt to go beyond the Law, and beyond the Right Execution of that Authority that the King and the Law hath inveſted them with.</p>
            <p>And therefore a particular Account of thoſe Statutes by which the Proteſtant Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are Proſecuted to their great dammage, for ſuch things as they do humbly conclude to be the matters of their God, with ſome ſober Conſiderations upon the ſaid Laws, take as followeth.</p>
            <p>The Proteſtant Diſſenters are in ſome places Proſecuted by the Statute <hi>Anno primo, Reginae Elizabethae</hi> Chapter 2. paragraph 14. where it is Ordained, <hi>That all and every Perſon and Perſons inhabiting within this Realm or any other the Queens Dominions ſhall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort to their Pariſh Church or Chappel, or to ſome uſual place where Common-Prayer and ſuch Service of God ſhall be ſued upon every Sunday and other days, ordained and ſued to be kept as Holy-days, and then and there to abide orderly and ſoberly, during the time of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer, Preaching or other Service of God, there to be uſed and miniſtred, upon pain of puniſhment by the Cenſures of the Church, and alſo upon pain that every perſon ſo offending, ſhall forfeit for every ſuch Offence Twelve-pence, to be Levied by the Church Wardens of the Pariſh where ſuch Offence ſhall be done, to the uſe of the Poor of the ſame Pariſh, of the Goods Lands and Tenements of ſuch Offendor, by way of Distreſs.</hi> And in Paragraph 20. It is Enacted, <hi>That no perſon or perſons ſhall be Impeached or otherwiſe Molested for any of the Offences in the ſaid Act, unleſs he or they ſo offending, be thereof Indicted at the next Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Seſſions to be holden before any ſuch Juſtices of</hi> Oyer and Terminer, <hi>or Juſtices of Aſſize next after any Offence committed or done contrary to the Tenor of this Act.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the better underſtanding of the aforeſaid Act, let the whole of it be peruſed as it is in the Statute-Book, however a brief account you ſhall have as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61106:5"/>
            <p n="1">I. A confirmation of the Book of Common-prayer, and Adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, as it was in the fifth and ſixth years of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, ſee <hi>Paragraph</hi> 1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>That if any Parſon, Vicar, or Miniſter, ſhall Refuſe to uſe the ſaid Book of Common-Prayer, or to Miniſter the Sacraments in ſuch Order and Form as is mentioned in the ſaid Book, in any Cathedral or Pariſh-Church, or other places; or that ſhall uſe any other Form or Order of Celebrating the Sacraments, or that ſhall uſe any Mattens or Even Songs, or other publick Prayers then is mentioned in the ſaid Book, or that ſhall Preach, Declare or Speak anything in the Derogation or Depraving of the ſaid Book, or any part thereof; And ſhall be Lawfully Convict thereof by the Verdict of Twelve men, ſhall for his firſt Offence forfeit all his Spiritual Benefices or Promotions, for one whole year next after his Conviction, and ſhall ſuffer Impriſonment for the Space of ſix Months; and for ſuch Offence, a ſecond time being Convict, ſhall ſuffer Impriſonment a whole year; and ſhall be Deprived</hi> Ipſo Facto, <hi>of all his Spiritual Promotions: and for the third Offence, being Convict thereof, ſhall be Deprived of all his Spiritual Promotions, and ſuffer impriſonment during his Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And if the Perſon that ſhall offend ſhall ot be beneficed, nor have any Spiritual Promotion, and be thereof Convicted, ſhall ſuffer Impriſonment one whole year, for the firſt Offence, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Bail or Mainpriſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And if any ſuch Perſon not having any Spiritual Promotion, ſhall be Convict of ſuch ſecond Offence, ſhall ſuffer Impriſonment during his Life.</hi> See Paragraph 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p n="3">III. It is further Enacted, <hi>That if any Perſon or Perſons whatſoever, ſhall in any Interludes Playes or Songs, Rhimes, or other Words, Declare or Speak any thing in the Derogation, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praving or Deſpiſing of the ſame Book, or ſhall Compel, or Procure, or Maintain any Parſon, Vicar or other Miniſter, to ſing or ſay any Common or open Prayer, or to Miniſter any Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment otherwiſe, or in any other manner and Form then is mentioned in the ſaid Book, or ſhall by any of the ſaid meanes Interrupt of Let any Parſon, Vicar, or other Miniſter, to ſing or ſay Common or open Prayer in any Cathedral, or Church, or Chappel, or any other place; ſhall for the first Offence being Lawfully Convict thereof, Forfeit an hundred Marks, and for the ſecond ſuch like Offence forfeit four hundred Marks, and for the third Offence being Lawfully Convict, ſhall forfeit all his Goods and Chattles, and ſuffer Impriſonment during Life.</hi> See Paragraph 9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That it is further Enacted, <hi>That whoſoever of the Inhabitants of this Realm,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that ſhall not come to their Pariſh-Church or Chappel, or other place of Common-Prayer, where it uſually ſaid, ſhall forfeit Twelve-pence for every</hi> Sunday <hi>and Holy-day.</hi> See Paragraph 14.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now from this Statute let theſe following Particulars be Soberly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</head>
               <p n="1">1. That this Statute was made in the firſt year of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, preſently upon the Caſting out, and throwing down of Popery.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That by this Statute the Proteſtant Religion was Revived and Confirmed, and ſo the Reformation was further carried on, as it was in the Reign of that happy Prince, <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Sixth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider that at the time of making this Statute, the whole Realm did Conſiſt of Proteſtants and Papiſts, Conſidered as Clergy and Layity. The Realm was not then acquainted with ſuch a thing as Proteſtant-Diſſenters, and therefore it cannot be fairly ſuppoſed that this Act was intended for ſuch, barely as ſuch; but the Deſign of this Act was, <hi>Firſt,</hi> To ſettle a Proteſtant-Miniſtry, to manage the Proteſtant Religion accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Light of that day: <hi>Secondly,</hi> To Remove all ſuch as were Popiſhly affected from Miniſterial Office, that ſo they might not keep the Queens Subjects in Popiſh Blindneſs: <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To bring the People from Popery to the Proteſtant Religion; and therefore a gentle way of Puniſhment was Provided, <hi>viz.</hi> Twelve-pence forfeit for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>Sunday</hi> and <hi>Holy-Day,</hi> for not coming to the place of Common-Prayer, ſo as to hear it and attend it. Now if the poor Proteſtant-Diſſenters muſt be puniſhed by Law for their Non-Conformity, let ſuch as are in Authority conſider that this Law will not do their Fellow Proteſtants ſo much harm as ſome other Laws; and yet this Puniſhment of Twelve-pence a day is a heavy Puniſhment for ſuch Poor People as are not worth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61106:6"/>Twelve-pence; and more eſpecially if five, or ten, or twenty days Forfeits be laid upon ſuch Poor People.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſider that though this be a gentle way of Puniſhment, yet there is no Word of God will Juſtifie it; for God hath not appointed any kind of Fines or Forfeitures, great or ſmall, as a Puniſhment for not Conforming to his Worſhip; and if either Papiſt or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant ſhould Conform only to avoid this or any other Puniſhment, they would be but Hypocrites, the Conformity being only to ſave their Purſes, and not the Act of their Spirits.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Conſider that in the Strictneſs of this Statute, if Proteſtants may be Proſecuted, great Numbers of thoſe that are Church-Proteſtants are a kind of Non-Conformiſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not go to Common-Prayer upon every <hi>Holy-day;</hi> and ſurely they would be loth to be ſo Proſecuted themſelves, as they Proſecute their Fellow Proteſtants.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The next Statute by which the Proteſtant Diſſenters are Proſecuted and Diſtreſſed, which now ſhall be Diſcourſed, is, <hi>Anno Viceſſimo Tertio Reginae Elizabethae,</hi> Chap. 1. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph 5.</p>
               <p>Where it is Enacted, <hi>That every Perſon above the Age of Sixteen years, which ſhall not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to ſome Church, Chappel, or uſual place of Common-Prayer, but forbear the ſame, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Tenor of a Statute, made in the firſt year of her Majeſties Reign, for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of Common-Prayer, and being Lawfully Convicted, ſhall forfeit to the Queens Majeſty for every Month, Twenty Pounds of</hi> Engliſh <hi>Lawful Money.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for the better Underſtanding of the aforeſaid Statute, it will be beſt to peruſe the whole of it, as it is in the Statute Book of the Realm; in which it will evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that it was Deſigned directly againſt thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion.</p>
               <p>See Paragraph 1. where there is mention made of <hi>divers ill Affected Perſons, who uſed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ways and means to withdraw her Majeſties Subjects from their due Obedience, to obey the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Authority of</hi> Rome.</p>
               <p>See Paragraph 2. where it is Enacted, <hi>That all Perſons whatſoever that ſhall abſolve, or by any Ways or Meanes perſwade the</hi> Queens <hi>Subjects from their Natural Obedience, to any Obedience to the Pretended Authority of the See of</hi> Rome, <hi>or of any other Prince, State or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate, to be had or uſed within her D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>minions, ſhall be Judged as Traytors, and ſhall ſuffer as Traytors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See Paragraph 3. And it is likewiſe Enacted, <hi>That every Perſon and Perſons that ſhall be willingly Aiders or Maintainers of ſuch Perſons, or ſhall conceal and not Diſcloſe ſuch Offences, ſhall be Tryed and Judged, and ſuffer as Offenders in Miſpriſion of Treaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See Paragraph 4. It is likewiſe Enacted, <hi>That every Perſon which ſhall ſay or ſing Maſs, being Lawfully Convicted, ſhall forfeit the Sum of two hundred Marks, and be Committed to the next Goal, there to Remain for the ſpace of one year; and that every Perſon which ſhall willingly hear Maſs, ſhall forfeit one Hundred Marks, and Suffer Impriſonment a year.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in Paragraph 5. It is Enacted, <hi>That every Perſon above the Age of Sixteen years, which ſhall not Repair to ſome Church or Chappel, or uſual place of Common-Prayer, ſhall For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit for every Month the Sum of Twenty Pounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From which Particulars of the aforeſaid Statute, let theſe following things be Conſidered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A further Confirmation of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Authority of the Queen, as a Proteſtant Monarch in her own Realm, in Oppoſition to any Pretended Authority by the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> is plainly Aſſerted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A further Proceed in providing Puniſhments for thoſe that ſhall maintain the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Rome</hi> in this Realm, and any manner of ways endeavour to withdraw the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>England,</hi> to obey the Authority of <hi>Rome,</hi> in Oppoſition to the Authority of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarch.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It ſeems by this Statute that after Twenty three years Reign of this Proteſtant Queen, the Popiſh Party were ſtill buſy in maintaining the Authority of <hi>Rome,</hi> and were not brought to ſubmit to the Proteſtant Religion, and therefore further Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61106:6"/>is made by a greater Penalty to Reduce them, <hi>viz.</hi> from Twelve-pence a day, unto Twenty pounds a Month.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And though this Statute doth mention every perſon above the Age of Sixteen years, as being Required to come to Church; there is good Ground to conclude, That by <hi>every Perſon</hi> was intended every <hi>ſuch</hi> perſon as abſented by Reaſon of their being of the <hi>Popiſh Religion,</hi> and Adhering unto the Authority of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any Forreign Jurisdiction, and thereby declared themſelves to be implacable, and Irreconcilable Enemies to the Government, both in Church and State.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Conſider that if the Law-makers had intended ſuch as are now called Proteſtant-Diſſenters, ſuch would have been Diſtinguiſhed from the Popiſh Party by ſome other Name, as it is in the Statute of the <hi>35th</hi> of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which ſhall be next Diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of; and therefore to Proſecute the Proteſtant Diſſenters by this Law, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly was made againſt the Papiſts, and is doubtful whether it was made againſt any Proteſtants, ſeemeth to be hard dealing; eſpecially conſidering that there are other Laws by which the Proteſtant Diſſenters have been, and ſtill are greatly Diſtreſſed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Conſider the greatneſs of this Puniſhment, <hi>viz.</hi> of the Forfeiture of Twenty pound a Month, for not Reparing to ſome Church of Chappel, or uſual place of Common-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; for though a Perſon may be Indicted but for one Month, and be Convicted thereof, he ſhall forfeit Twenty pounds a Month all the time after ſuch Conviction, until he ſhall make ſuch Submiſſion in a way of Conformity as the Law doth Require, without any more Indictments or Convictions.</p>
               <p>See this in the Statute, <hi>Anno Viceſſimo nono Reginae Elizabethae, Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>Paragraph</hi> 3, 4. Where it is Enacted, <hi>That ſuch Offendor ſhall alſo for every Month after ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, without any other Indictment or Conviction, pay into the Receipt of the</hi> Exchequer, <hi>after the Rate or Twenty pounds for every Month after ſuch Conviction.</hi> So that after this Rate, ſuch Offender will forfeit Two Hundred and Three-ſcore pounds a year, there being according to Law, thirteen Months in the year.</p>
               <p>And it is further Provided, by this laſt-mentioned Statute, <hi>That if default ſhall be made in any part of any Payment aforeſaid, that then and ſo often the</hi> Queens <hi>Majeſty ſhall and may by Proceſs out of the ſaid</hi> Exchequer, <hi>Take, Seize, and injoy all the Goods, and Two Parts as well of all the Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments Lyable to ſuch Seizures, Leaving the third part only of the ſame Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, Leaſes and Farms, to and for the Maintenance and Relief of the ſame Offender, his Wife, Children and Family.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for a further demonſtration of this Matter, that theſe forementioned Act, <hi>viz</hi> 23. and 29. <hi>Eliz.</hi> were made and deſigned for the Popiſh Party, is further evident by the Statute of <hi>Primo Jacobi Regis,</hi> Chap. 4. the Title of which Act is thus: <hi>An Act for the due Execution of the Statutes against Jeſuites, Seminary Prieſts, Recuſants,</hi> &amp;c. And the firſt part of this Act is to confirm and to put in Execution all thoſe Statutes in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> againſt Jeſuites, Seminary Prieſts, and other ſuch-like Prieſts, and alſo againſt all manner of Recuſants.</p>
               <p>Now by thoſe words, <hi>Jeſuites, Seminary Prieſts, and other ſuch-like Prieſts,</hi> are to be underſtood all the ſeveral Orders of Eccleſiaſtical Perſons belonging to, and owning of the Authority of <hi>Rome;</hi> as doth appear by ſome words in the firſt Paragraph of the ſaid Statute, <hi>viz. Eccleſiaſtical Perſons whatſoever, made, ordained, or profeſſed, or to be made, ordained, or profeſſed, by any Authority or Juriſdiction derived, challenged, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, from the See of</hi> Rome.</p>
               <p>And by theſe words, <hi>all manner of Recuſants,</hi> are to be underſtood all manner and ſorts of Perſons, Reſpecting their Degrees, Conſidered of the Layity, belonging to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> For, in as much as <hi>Recuſants</hi> are joyned with <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> it muſt be underſtood of <hi>Popiſh Recuſants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is further Evident by and from the Statute of <hi>Anno Tertio Jacobi Regis,</hi> Chap: 4. The Title of which Act is thus: <hi>An Act for the better diſcovering and Repreſſing of Popiſh Recuſants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Now from the Title of this Statute Conſider that <hi>Popiſh Recuſants</hi> are the only Perſons mentioned, and therefore the Statute it ſelf ought ſo to be underſtood, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61106:7"/>provided for the better Diſcovery and Repreſſing of them, and no others; Except that any particular Paſſage in the ſaid Statute doth mention any others, as diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Popiſh Recuſants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. And therefore let the Statute it ſelf be Conſidered in all the Paragraphs, whether any others of the Kings Subjects (not being Papiſts) are at all concerned in the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties of the ſaid Statutes, <hi>viz</hi> 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and 29 <hi>Eliz.</hi> which are particularly mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this Statute, provided to puniſh Perſons for not coming to Common-Prayer or the Sacrament. Take a brief Account of the ſaid Statute, Reſpecting not coming to Church and Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the firſt Paragraph of the ſaid Statute the Authority of the Realm took notice, that <hi>divers Perſons Popiſhly Affected did ſometimes Repare to Church, to eſcape the Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Laws in that behalf provided, who notwithſtanding did adhere in their Hearts to the Popiſh Religion; and ſo by the Infection drawn from thence, were ready to Entertain and Execute any Treaſonable Conſpiracies; as did Evidently appear by that more then barbarous and horrible Attempt to have blown up with Gunpowder the King, Queen Prince, Lords and Commons, Aſſembled in Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. In paragraph the Second and Third, It is Enacted for the better diſcovery of ſuch Evil Perſons, viz. <hi>Every Popiſh Recuſant Convicted, or that ſhould be Convicted, and that ſhould afterward Conform, to come to Church and Common Prayer, ſhould alſo take and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament once in every year following; and if they did not, then they ſhould forfeit for the firſt year Twenty Pounds, and for the ſecond year Forty Pounds, And for every year after Threeſcore Pounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. In the Fourth Paragraph it is Enacted, <hi>That the Church-Wardens and Conſtables of their Reſpective Towns or Pariſhes, and Chief Conſtables of the Hundred, ſhall preſent the Monthly Abſence from Church of all manner of</hi> POPISH RECUSANTS <hi>within ſuch Towns and Pariſhes</hi> (Mark thoſe plain words of the ſaid Statute) it is not ſaid they ſhall Preſent Proteſtants, but Popiſh Recuſants.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In Paragraph the fifth it is Enacted, <hi>That ſuch Church Wardens, Conſtables and High-Conſtables, for every Default in not Preſenting ſuch Recuſants, ſhall forfeit Twenty Shillings; and if they do make ſuch Preſentments, they ſhall be Recorded by the Clerk of the Seſſions without any Fee, on Forty Shillings Forfeit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. In Paragraph the ſixth it is Enacted, <hi>That every Church-Warden, Conſtable and High-Conſtable, as ſhall make ſuch Preſentment, ſo as the Party ſhall be Indicted and Convicted, ſhall have for Reward, Forty Shillings, to be Levied out of the Recuſants Goods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. In Paragraph 10. A Repetition is made of that part of the Statute of the Twenty Third of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> concerning the Forfeiture of <hi>Twenty Pound a Month</hi> for not come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Church.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In Paragraph 11. There is a Recitation of that part of the Statute of the 29th of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> concerning the Queens having power by the ſaid Statute to ſeiz upon all the Goods, and two parts of the Lands and Tenements, Leaſes and Farms of ſuch Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon Default of the Non Payment of the aforeſaid Twenty Pounds a Month, and let the Offender injoy the third part of his Lands and Tenements, Leaſes and Farms for the maintenance of his Family. And then this Statute, <hi>viz.</hi> The Third of King <hi>James,</hi> doth further provided, <hi>That the King ſhall have power to Refuſe the Twenty Pound a Month, though the Offender be ready to pay it according to the Statute of 29th of</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>and if he pleaſe, may Take, Seiz, and injoy the two parts of the Offenders Eſtate;</hi> and the reaſon for ſo doing was, becauſe the Popiſh Party, who were men of great Eſtates could bear the payment of Twenty Pounds a Month, and ſo Retain the Reſidue of their Livings and inheritance in their own hands, which as the ſaid Statute ſaith, was for the moſt part imployed to the Maintenance of Superſtition and Popiſh Religion, and to the Relief of Jeſuits, Seminary Prieſts, and other dangerons perſons to the State.</p>
               <p>Now from theſe things ſoberly conſidered, in comparing one Statute with another, it ſeemeth evident that the aforeſaid Statutes were deſigned and intended for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, they being ſo often mentioned in plain words, <hi>viz. Jeſuits, Seminary Prieſts, and other Prieſts and Deacons belonging to the See of</hi> Rome, <hi>and all manner of Popiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants;</hi> and no mention of any other perſons diſtinguiſhed from the Papiſts.</p>
               <p>And therefore it ſeemeth hard meaſure that ſuch as are known and ſufficiently owned to be Proteſtants by the ſeveral Neighbourhoods where they dwell, throughout this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61106:7"/>Kingdom, ſhould be Proſecuted by ſuch Laws in which they are not at all mentioned; eſpecially ſeeing there are other Laws by which they are ſufficiently diſtreſſed.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Another Law by which the Proteſtant Diſſenters have been and ſtill are Lyable to be Proſecuted, is the Statute of <hi>Anno Triceſſimo quinto Reginae Elizabethae,</hi> Chap. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In which Statute theſe things are Enacted and Provided:</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> That if any Perſon or Perſons above the Age of Sixteen years, ſhall obſtinately Refuſe to Repair to ſome Church, Chappel, or uſual place of Common-Prayer, by the Space of a Month, to hear Divine Service Eſtabliſhed by her Majeſties Laws, or ſhall by Printing, Writing, or Expreſs Words or Speeches, Adviſedly or purpoſely Practice or go about to move any of her Majeſties Subjects, or any others, to deny, withſtand, or impugn her Majeſties Power and Authority in Caſes Eccleſiaſtical, or ſhall Adviſedly and Maliciouſly move or perſwade any other Perſon to forbear to come to Church, to hear Divine Service, or the Communion, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her Majeſties Laws, or to come to, or be preſent at any <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful Aſſemblies, Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, or Meetings, under Colour or Pretence of any Exerciſe of Religion, contrary to her Majeſties ſaid Laws and Statutes, or ſhall willingly join in, or be preſent at any ſuch Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, Conventicles, or Meetings, that then every ſuch Offender being Lawfully Convicted, ſhall be Committed to Priſon, there to Remain without Bail or Mainprize, until they ſhall Conform and Yield themſelves to come to ſome Church or Chappel, or uſual place of Common-Prayer, and hear Divine Service. <hi>See Paragraph 1.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. It is Provided in the ſame Statute,</hi> That if ſuch Offender ſo Convict as aforeſaid, ſhall not Conform in coming to Church, to hear Divine Service, and to make ſuch open Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion as is after appointed by this Statute, being Required thereunto, within the Space of three Months, after Conviction by the Biſhop of the Dioceſs, or any Juſtice of Peace of the County where the Perſon ſhall happen to be, or by the Miniſter or Curate of the Pariſh, That then every ſuch Offender upon his being warned and Required by any Justice of Peace of the ſame County, ſhall upon his Corporal Oath abjure this Realm, and all other her Majeſties Dominions and Countreys, and ſhall not Return without Licence from her Majeſty. <hi>See Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph 2.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3. It is Provided,</hi> That if ſuch Offender ſhall Refuſe to make ſuch Abjuration as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or after Objuration made, ſhall not depart out of this Realm according to this preſent Act, or after ſuch his Departure, ſhall Return again without her Majeſties Licence, that then in every ſuch Caſe the Perſon offending ſhall be Adjudged a Fellon, and ſhall ſuffer as in the Caſe of Fellony, without the Benefit of Clergy. <hi>See Paragraph 3.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4. It is further Enacted,</hi> That if ſuch Offender before he or they be ſo warned or Required to make Abjuration, ſhall Repair to ſome Pariſh-church on ſome <hi>Sunday</hi> or Feſtival Day, and there hear Divine Service, and make Publick and open Submiſſion, and Declaration, of his and their Conformity, that then the ſame Offender ſhall be clearly diſcharged of all the Penalties and Puniſhments Inflicted or Impoſed by this Act.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Form of Submiſſion is as followeth, <hi>See Paragraph</hi> 4.</head>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> I <hi>A B.</hi> Do humbly Confeſs and Acknowledge, That I have grievouſly Offended God, in Contemning her Majeſties Godly and Lawful Government and Authority, by abſenting my ſelf from Church, and from hearing Divine Service, contrary to the Godly Laws and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this Realm, and in uſing and frequenting Diſordered and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful Conventicles and Aſſemblies, under Pretence and Colour of Exerciſe of Religion: And I am heartily ſorry for the ſame, and do Acknowledge and teſtify in my Conſcience, That no other Perſon hath or ought to have Power over her Majeſty; and I do promiſe and proteſt, without any diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or any Colour or means of any Diſpenſation, that from henceforth I will from time to time obey and perform her Majeſties Laws and Statutes, in Reparing to the Church, to hear Divine Service, and do my utmoſt indeavour to maintain and defend the ſame, <hi>See Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph 5.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6. It is alſo Provided by this Act.</hi> That no Popiſh Recuſant, or Feme-Covert, ſhall be Compelled, or bound to Abjure by Vertue of this Act, <hi>See Paragraph 12.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7. It is further Provided by this Statute,</hi> That every Perſon that ſhall Abjure, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61106:8"/>to Abjure, being Required thereunto as aforeſaid, ſhall forfeit and loſe to her Majeſty all his Goods and Chattles for ever, and ſhall further loſe all his Lands, Tenements and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments, for and during the Life only of ſuch Offender, &amp; no longer, and that the Wife of ſuch Offender ſhall not loſe her Dower, and that the Heir of ſuch Offender, after the Death of ſuch Offender, ſhall have and injoy the Lands Tenements and Hereditaments of ſuch Offender.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From this Statute let theſe things be Conſidered.</head>
               <p n="1">1. That it is Evident this Statute was made for the puniſhing of ſueh as were not at all accounted Papiſts, or Popiſh Recuſants, and this will appear in theſe following Reaſons; <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe the deſign of the Statute was for the preventing and avoiding of great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies and Perils as might happen and grow by the wicked and dangerous Practices of <hi>Seditious Sectaries,</hi> and diſloyal Perſons: Now this word <hi>Seditious Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> doth diſtinguiſh ſome Perſons from thoſe, that by the Law of this Realm are called <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Popiſh Recuſants; Secondly,</hi> Becauſe <hi>Popiſh Recuſants</hi> are exempted from Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring of the Realm, by vertue of the aforeſaid Statute, which is a plain Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the Severity of this ſame Law was made and intended for ſuch as were not <hi>Papiſts</hi> or <hi>Popiſh Recuſants;</hi> and therefore good Reaſon to conclude that thoſe other Statutes in which mention is made, of the <hi>Popiſh Party</hi> were made only againſt them, and not againſt ſuch as are in this Statute called <hi>Sectaries,</hi> who are not <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider how thoſe perſons are deſcribed for whom the puniſhments of this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute are Provided, <hi>viz.</hi> Seditious Sectaries and Diſloyal Perſons: See Paragraph 1. And for as much as this Law hath been put in Execution againſt the Proteſtant Diſſenters, it is meet to inquire whether they are in very deed ſuch perſons, <hi>viz.</hi> Seditious Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Diſloyal Perſons.</p>
               <p>It is one thing for perſons to be called and reputed ſuch, and another thing to be ſuch indeed and in truth. The city of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was called and counted a City of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and Sedition, <hi>See Ezra.</hi> 4.19.</p>
               <p>The Bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was Accuſed of Sedition, and being a Ring-leader therein, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 24.5. <hi>For we have found this man a Peſtilent Fellow, and a Mover of Sedition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the</hi> Jews <hi>throughout the world, and a Ring-leader of the Sect of the</hi> Nazareens; thus it is evident from the Holy Scripture that the beſt of perſons have gone under the worſt names, being deemed ſuch as indeed they are not; our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt was called a Devil, <hi>yea Belzebub the Prince of the Devils,</hi> and he was Proſecuted unto death, as being a Blaſphemer; and therefore it muſt not be wondred at, if thoſe that are now moſt pure in the Profeſſion and Practire of the Chriſtian Religion, be called Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Sectaries and Diſloyal Perſons; though indeed and in truth they are not ſuch, as may be truly ſaid of the Proteſtant Diſſenters.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are not Seditious Perſons, becauſe they make the Word of God the Rule of their Faith and Practice promoting the Chriſtian Religion in every part of it, as it is in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Popery according to the beſt of their light and knowledg in the Holy Scriptures, endeavouring to live a Holy Life and Converſation, ſuitable to ſuch a Holy Profeſſion, and therefore ought to be deemed good Proteſtants, though in ſome things they differ from the Church-Proteſtants; eſpecially conſidering that thoſe things in the Proteſtant Religion wherein both Parties do agree, are greater than thoſe things wherein they do differ; and yet thoſe things wherein they differ are ſuch as each Party cannot Conform to, without wronging of their Conſciences; and doubtleſs the Church-Proteſtants would think it hard meaſure if they ſhould be forced to Conform to the Diſſenters, even as the Diſſenters think it hard meaſure to be forced to Conform to the Church-Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>And therefore each Party ſhould labour to walk by that Golden Rule that Chriſt hath given in Mat. 7.12. <hi>Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, do you even to them for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Proteſtant Diſſenters cannot fairly be deemed Diſloyal Perſons, forasmuch as they do acknowledg the King to be Supream Governour of this Realm, and all other His Majeſties Dominions and Countries, in oppoſition to the Pope and all Forreign Juriſdiction, and are ready with their Purſe and Perſons to maintain the Kings Perſon and Crown againſt all Murdering Conſpiracies among any ſort of perſons whatſoever.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:61106:8"/>
               <p>And though it may be objected, that ſome under the name of Proteſtant-Diſſenters have been charged with and have been found guilty of the aforeſaid Wickedneſs; God forbid that this ſhould be charged upon the whole Party, for as much as it is well known that the generality of the Proteſtant Diſſenters do abhor ſuch Principles and Practices, and do as heartily deſire that the King may injoy his Crown and Kingdom free from all violence, as they deſire to injoy their own Habitarions and other their Lawful Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. What though ſome Gentlemen, ſome Knights, ſome Peers of the Realm, be charged and found guilty of Diſloyalty; yet it would be very unrighteous to charge or deem all of ſuch Degrees or Titles to be ſo guilty of the like Diſloyalty.</p>
               <p>However Non-Conformity barely of it ſelf, cannot be fairly accounted Diſloyalty, they that will ſay ſo, may well be counted ſuch as condemn the Generation of the Righteous in all Ages; even the Apoſtles and Diſciples of our Lord Jeſus, they were the Non-Conformiſts of that day: and yet they were Loyal Subjects under all thoſe Governments where the Providence of God did caſt them; and the Apoſtle, <hi>Paul</hi> tho' he did Preach up Subjection to Authority, yet he did maintain his Non-Conformity, in matters of Religion; and the Chriſtians in queen <hi>Maries</hi> days, did maintain their Non-Conformity, in not ſubmitting to the Religion, as it was Eſtabliſhed by Law, and yet they were Loyal Subjects; and ſo it may be truly ſaid of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, their Non-Conformity doth not deſtroy their Loyalty. Thus it is evident that Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity is conſiſtent with true Loyalty. Yet it may be further Demonſtrated, that Non-Conformity may be attended with the greateſt Loyalty, when Conformity may be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with the greateſt Diſloyalty, as doth appear in that famous inſtance of <hi>Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ai,</hi> who was a Notorious Non-Conformiſt, in not ſubmitting to the Eſtabliſhed Worſhip of that Kingdom; and yet ſuch was his Loyalty, that he diſcovered the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of two of the Kings Chamberlains, who may well be concluded to be the Conformiſts in Religious matters, and yet deſigned to deprive the King of his Life; but <hi>Mordecai</hi> the Non-Conformiſt did ſave the Kings life, though he went ſome conſiderable time Unrewarded for that his Loyal Service.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider that the Puniſhment of this Statute is too great for the Offences, <hi>viz.</hi> of not coming to Church to hear Common-Prayer, &amp; of frequenting Conventicles; if by Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles are meant only ſuch Meetings where there is the Exerciſe of Religion, as it is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Proteſtant Diſſenters; the Puniſhments provided by this Act being of ſeveral ſorts, 1. Impriſonment, 2. Abjuration, 3. Death, if Abjuration be Refuſed, 4. Loſs of all Goods for ever. 5. Loſs of all Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, during the Life of the Offender; and all this for not coming to hear Common-prayer, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting of ſuch Religious Meetings as are called Conventicles.</p>
               <p>Now it ſeemeth very ſtrange, that ſo ſevere a Law ſhould be made by a Proteſtant Queen, and by a Proteſtant Parliament, againſt any Perſons that could not in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence Submit to that form of Religion Eſtabliſhed by Law, who notwithſtanding were Proteſtants, and did own, approve, and promote the Proteſtant Religion, in the main and Subſtantial parts of it: Eſpecially conſidering how the ſaid queen, and thoſe Aſſembled in the aforeſaid Parliament, did groan under the Government of Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> becauſe their Conſciences were impoſed upon, by Reaſon of the <hi>Popiſh Religion,</hi> which then was Eſtabliſhed by Law; and then the Poor Proteſtants were deemed no better then <hi>Sectaries, Schiſmaticks,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and their Religious Meetings, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they could get together, were accounted Seditious Conventicles, and Rebellious Meetings; and they were Proſecuted both by the Eccleſiaſtical and the Temporal Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, even unto Death.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſider that though queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did give the Royal Aſſent unto this Act of Parliament, ſhe was greatly troubled when Mr. <hi>Henry Barrow,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Greenwood</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Penry,</hi> were put to Death for their Non-Conformity; ſhe being inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome (of whom ſhe demanded an Account of their Death, they being at that time preſent) That they were very Eminent Chriſtians, and that if they had lived, they might have been as worthy Inſtruments for the Church of God, as hath been raiſed in this Age, at which her Majeſty ſighed.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Conſider that though this Act hath been continued from time to time, yet there hath been a ceſſation of the Executing of it, from the latter end of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, to the Reign of this preſent Majeſty.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:61106:9"/>
               <p n="6">6. Conſider that though ſome Juſtices of the Peace have attempted to put this Act in Execution, ſince his Majeſties Reſtauration, whereby a conſiderable Number of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant-Diſſenters were Convicted at <hi>Aylesbury,</hi> and all their Goods in their ſhops and houſes were ſeized, and they were in great danger of being quickly hanged, but thanks be to God, his Majeſty had Compaſſion, Judging it too hard dealings for his Proteſtant Subjects; and ſo he not only ſaved their Lives, but Reſtored them all their Goods, which Gracious Proceedings of the King was agreeable to his Royal Promiſe, in his Royal Declaration from <hi>Breda,</hi> in theſe words:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We do Declare a Liberty to tender Conſciences, and that no man ſhall be diſquieted or called in Queſtion, for differences in opinion in matters of Religion, which do not diſturb the Peace of the Kingdom, and that We ſhall be ready to conſent to ſuch an Act of Parliament, as upon Mature Deliberation ſhall be offered to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s for the full granting ſuch Indulgence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Conſider that the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, even of late years, did take into their wiſe and ſerious Conſideration this very Statute, and by joynt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had prepared a Bill for the Repealing of the ſame, that ſo the Kings Proteſtant Subjects might be no more in danger of it; but behold there was an unhappy failure in Mr. <hi>Somebody</hi> that it was not preſented to his Majeſty at the time when other Bills were preſented and had the Royal aſſent, however for as much as Lords and Commons had agreed unto it, and His Majeſty did not Reject it; it ſeemeth to be the voice of the Kingdom, that this aforeſaid Statute ſhould not be put in Execution.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Sometimes the Proteſtant Diſſenters are diſtreſſed in being Proſecuted by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the 7th. of <hi>Jacobi,</hi> which Statute doth provide the Puniſhment of Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for Refuſing to take the Oath of Allegiance, and in Refuſing of it ſo often as the Law provideth for the tendering of it, that then the ſaid Perſon ſhall incur a <hi>Premunire;</hi> Now, there are great Numbers of his Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects, who are Diſſenters, who have and can freely take the ſaid Oath; and there be many others who are Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that cannot take the ſaid Oath: <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe they think it is Unlawful to ſwear in any Caſe, becauſe Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all. Secondly,</hi> Some cannot take the ſaid Oath, becauſe they think a Promiſſary Oath is not Lawful. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Some cannot take the ſaid Oath, becauſe they think that they are thereby bound to an Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Obedience, and Performance of all the Laws of the Realm, and from thence concinde that they are bound to go to Church, and to take the Sacrament, and to forbear to go to ſuch Religious Meetings as are called Conventicles; and therefore with Patience they do rather Submit to the Puniſhment of the ſaid Law, for Refuſing the ſaid Oath.</p>
               <p>But others of the Diſſenters are otherways perſwaded concerning the aforeſaid Oath, and the aforeſaid Particulars, as the Opinions of their fellow Diſſenters; <hi>Firſt,</hi> they think Chriſt hath not forbid all kind of Swearing whatſoever, but by theſe words, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> they underſtand not at all to ſwear by thoſe things mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Earth, <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Temple, the Altar, or any other thing below God himſelf</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> They do not think that a Promiſary Oath is unlawful, becauſe it is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to make a Promiſe, and thereby bind themſelves to the Performance of any lawful matter contained in ſuch Promiſe, and therefore if the matter of an Oath be lawful, they think they may as well ſwear to Perform it as promiſe to perform it; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the matter being between the King and Subject, and the Swearing being the moſt ſollemn way of aſſuring the performance of the matters promiſed, and of believing the matters aſſerted in the ſaid Oath. And ſo end that Controverſy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They cannot think or believe that by the Oath they are Bound to an actual performance of all the Laws of the Realm for the Reaſons following.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe if they be ſo Bound, then are all the Kings Subjects who have taken the ſaid Oath ſo bound alſo, and then it fairly followeth, that if in any thing any Law be broken, then the ſaid Oath is broken, and the Perſons Allegiance to his King is Broken alſo which ſeemeth to be a harſh concluſion, becauſe then great multitudes of the Kings Subjects who are not Diſſenters muſt be deemed deeply guilty in this matter, <hi>viz.</hi> Such as ſwear, prophanely ſuch as curſe, ſuch as are drunk, ſuch as promote the Trade of French Wines muſt be adjudged for ſworn perſons &amp; breakers of their Allegiance, becauſe in theſe and divers other things they are Breakers of the Law which ſeemeth to be an uncharitable
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61106:9"/>concluſion concerning ſuch whom Authority doth deem Liege Subjects, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their Breaking the Laws by the aforeſaid Offences.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Such Diſſenters as can and do take the aforeſaid Oath, cannot think they are thereby bound actually to obey all the Laws of the Realm, and be bound by Oath to go to Church, and to take the Sacrament, and to for bear their Religious Meetings, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no ſuch thing is expreſſed in the ſaid Oath, and the Oath it ſelf doth but bind thoſe that take it according to the plain and expreſs words thereof. Let the laſt words of the Oath be well conſidered, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And all theſe things I do plainly and ſincerely Acknowledg and ſwear, according to the Expreſs Words by me ſpoken, and according to the plain and common ſenſe and underſtanding of the ſame words, without any Equivocation, or mental Evaſion, or ſecret Reſervation whatſoever; and I do make this Recognition and Acknowledgment, heartily, willingly, and truly, upon the True Faith of a Chriſtian, ſo help me God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From which part of the Oath, as it belongeth to the whole of the ſaid Oath, Let theſe things be Obſerved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That whatſoever thing is not in the expreſs words of the ſaid Oth, that is not ſworn unto, either as a negative or an affirmative.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the matter contained in the expreſs words muſt be underſtood, and ſo ſworn unto as doth agree with the common and known ſenſe of ſuch <hi>Engliſh</hi> Words, <hi>viz.</hi> Without ſtraining or ſtretching of the words beyond the litteral ſenſe of them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any equivocation or mental evaſion, or ſecret reſervation whatſoever, <hi>viz.</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cunning or ſecret or myſtical apprehenſion of the words of the ſaid Oath.</p>
               <p>Now the Particulars fairly expreſſed in the ſaid Oath, are theſe that follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A ſolemn aſſerting of the Kings Right to the Crown of this Realm, and other his Dominions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſolemn denying that the Pope of himſelf, nor by any Authority of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by any other means, hath any power or authority over the Kings Perſon, or over any of his Countries, or over any of his Subjects.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Solemn Reſolution to be true and faithful Subjects to the King, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any Declaration or Sentence of Excommunication, or Deprivation made or grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or to be made or granted by the <hi>Pope</hi> or his Succeſſors, or by any Authority derived or pretended to be derived from him, or his See againſt the ſaid King, his Heirs or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; and him and them will defend to the utmoſt of my power againſt all Conſpiracies and Attempts whatſoever, which ſhall be made againſt his or their Perſons, their Crown or Dignity, by reaſon or colour of any ſuch Sentence or Declaration, or otherwiſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That as ſuch ſhall not be guilty of Treaſon themſelves, ſo they are Bound to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover all Treaſons and Traiterous Conſpiracies they ſnall know among any others.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A. Solemn Renunciation of that Damnable Doctrine, That Princes which be Excommunicated or Deprived by the Pope, may be depoſed or murthered by their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, or any other whatſoever.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That the Pope, nor any other perſon whatſoever, hath power to abſolve from this Oath or any part thereof.</p>
               <p n="7">7. A Solemn Declaration that this Oath is taken ſincerely and not Hypocritically.</p>
               <p>Now for as much as many good Chriſtians do ſcruple the taking of the aforeſaid Oath by reaſon of their concluding, that they are thereby bound to more things then is preſſed in the ſaid Oath, and yet are well ſatisfied and Reſolved to defend the Kings Perſon, and maintain the welfare of the Kingdom againſt the Pope and all Forreign Power, and have given great demonſtration of their own peaceable ſubjection to His Majeſties Government, it ſeemeth to be a Proceedings of great ſeverity to puniſh ſuch perſons who fear ſwearing this Oath only leaſt they ſhould Sin againſt God, in ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which they know they cannot perform, <hi>viz.</hi> A thorow Conformity to the Church Matters, which if that were the meaning of the Oath, thoſe Nonconformiſts that have taken the ſaid Oath, would not have taken it,</p>
               <p>Now therefore that each Party may be helped in this matter here followeth a Copy of the Oath of Allegiance, and King <hi>James</hi> his Expoſition or Paraphraſe upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Oath of Allegiance.</label>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>Do truly and ſincerely acknowledg, Profeſs, Testifie and declare in my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, before God and the World, that our Sovereign Lord King</hi> James <hi>is Lawful and Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61106:10"/>King of this Realm, and of all other his Majeſties Dominions and Countries, and that that the Pope, neither of himſelf, nor by any Authority of the Church or</hi> See of Rome, <hi>or by any other means with any other, hath any power or authority to depoſe the King, or to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any of his Majeſties Kingdoms or Dominions, or to Authorize any Forreign Prince to invade or Annoy him or his Countries, or to diſcharge any of his Subjects of their Allegiance or Obedience to his Majeſty, or to give Licence or leave to any of them to bear Arms, to Raiſe Tumults, to offer any violence or hurt to His Majeſties Royal Perſon, State or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to any of His Majeſties Subjects within his Majeſties Dominions. Alſo I do ſwear from my Heart, that notwithſtanding any Declaration or Sentence of Excommunication or Deprivation made or granted, or to be made and granted by the Pope or his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, or by any Authority derived, or pretended to be derived from him, or his See againſt the ſaid King, his Heirs or Succeſſors, or any Abſolution of the ſaid Subjects from their Obedience; I will bear Faith and true Allegiance to his Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors, and him and them will defend to the utmoſt of my power againſt all Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Attempts whatſoever, which ſhall be made againſt his or their Perſons, their Crown and Dignity, by reaſon or colour of any ſuch Sentence or Declaration, or otherwiſe; And I will do my best endeavour, to diſcloſe and make known unto his Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors, all Treaſons and Traiterous Conſpiracies, which I ſhall know or hear of, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him or any of them; And I further ſwear, That I do from my heart abhor, deteſt and abjure as impious and heretical, this Damnable Doctrine and Poſition, that Princes which be Excommunicated or Deprived by the Pope, may be depoſed or murthered by their Subjects, or any other whatſoever; and I do believe and in my Conſcience am Reſolved, that neither the Pope, nor any other perſon whatſoever, hath power to abſolve me of this Oath, nor any part thereof, which I acknowledg by good and full Authority to be lawfully Miniſtred unto me; and do Renounce all Pardons and Diſpenſations to the contrary.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And all theſe things I do plainly and ſincerely Acknowledge and Swear, according to theſe Expreſs Words by me ſpoken, and according to the plain and common ſenſe and underſtanding of the ſame words without any Equivocation, or mental Evaſion, or ſecret Reſervation what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; and I do make this Recognition and Acknowledgment, heartily willingly and truly, upon the True Faith of a Chriſtian. So help me God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>And now for a further and better help to underſtand the Oath of Allegiance, let King <hi>James</hi> his anſwer to Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> be well conſidered concerning this Oath, in his Apologie for the Oath of Allegiance, <hi>page</hi> 46. where he ſaith,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may appear what unreaſonable and rebellious points he would drive my Subjects unto, by Refuſing the whole Body of that Oath, as it is conceived; for he that ſhall Refuſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> take this Oath, muſt of neceſſity hold all or ſome of theſe Propoſition following:</hi> viz.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That I King <hi>James</hi> am not the Lawful King of this Kingdom, and all other my Dominions.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Pope by his own Authority may depoſe me; if not by his own Authority, yet by ſome other Authority of the Church, or of the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> if not by ſome other Authority of the Church of See of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet by other means with others help he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe me.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the Pope may diſpoſe of my Kingdoms and Dominions.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That the Pope may give Authority to ſome Forreign Prince to invade my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That the Pope may diſcharge my Subjects from their Obedience and Allegiance to me.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. That the Pope may give Licence to one or more of my Subjects to bear Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. That the Pope may give leave to my Subjects to offer violence to my Perſon, or to my government, or to ſome of my Subjects.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. That if the Pope ſhall by Sentence Excommnnicate or Depoſe me, my Subjects are not to bear Faith and Allegiance to me.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. If the Pope ſhall by Sentence Excommunicate or Depoſe me, my Subjects are not bound to defend with all their power my Perſon and Crown.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. If the Pope ſhall give out any Sentence of Excommunication or Deprivation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, my Subjects by reaſon of that Sentence, are not bound to Reveal all Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies and Treaſons againſt me which ſhall come to their hearing or knowledge.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:61106:10"/>
                  <p n="11">11. That it is not Heretical or deteſtable to hold that Princes being Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Pope, may either depoſed or killed by their Subjects or any other.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. That the Pope hath power to abſolve my Subjects from this Oath, or from ſome part thereof.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. That this Oath is not Adminiſtred to my Subjects by a full and lawful Authority.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. That this Oath is to be taken with Equivocation, Mental Evaſion, or ſecret Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and not with the Heart and good-will, Sincerely, in the Faith of a Chriſtian Man.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Theſe are the true and natural Branches of the Body of this Oath.</p>
               <p>And now foraſmuch as there is another Oath, called the Oath of Supremacy, about which many good Proteſtants have differing Apprehenſions, ſome being very free to take the ſaid Oath, &amp; ſome do Conſcienciouſly ſcruple it, and ſo dare not take it for fear they ſhould Sin againſt God in ſo doing: The ſame Oath ſhall be here Preſented to Conſideration.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Oath of Supremacy.</label>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>Do utterly Teſtifie and Declare in my conſcience, That the Queens Highneſs is the only Supream Governour of this Realm, and of all other Her highneſs Dominions and Countries, as well in all Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Things or Cauſes, as Temporal: And that no Forreign Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State, or Potentate, hath, or ought to have any Jurisdiction, Power, Superiority, Pre-eminence or Authority Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Realm; and therefore I do utterly Renounce and Forſake all Forreign Jurisdictions, Powers, Superiorities and Authorities, and do promiſe that from henceforth I ſhall bear Faith and True Allegiance to the Queens Highneſs, her Heirs and Lawful Succeſſors, and to my power ſhall aſſiſt and defend all Juriſdictions, Priviledges, Pre-eminences and Authorities, granted or belonging to the Queens Highneſs, her Heirs or Succeſſors, or united and annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm, So help me God, and by the contents of this Book.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Now in the aforeſaid Oath, ſome of the words are ſuch as many Godly Perſons can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heartily ſpeak, and therefore Refuſe to ſpeak them at all in a way of Swearing, <hi>viz.</hi> That the King as Supream Governour of this Realm, is Supream Governour in all Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Things or Cauſes, as well as in all Temporal Things and Cauſes.</p>
               <p>Which words are Expounded or Explained by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in an Admonition Annexed to the Queens Injunctions: Publiſhed in the firſt year of her Raign, which take as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>And further, Her Majeſty forbiddeth all manner of Subjects to give Ear or Credit to ſuch perverſe and malitious perſons, which moſt ſiniſterly and malitiouſly labour to notify to her loving Subjects, how by the words of the ſaid Oath it may be Collected, the Kings or Queens of this Realm, Poſſeſſors of the Crown, may challenge Authority and Power of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of Divine Offices in the Church, wherein her ſaid Subjects be much Abuſed by ſuch evil diſpoſed perſons: For certainly Her Majeſty neither doth nor ever will challenge any other Authority, then that was Challenged, and lately uſed by the ſaid Noble Kings of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Memory, King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth, and King</hi> Edward <hi>the ſixth, which is and was of ancient time due to the Imperial Crown of this Realm, That is under God to have Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Rule over all manner of perſons Born within theſe her Realms, Dominions and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, of what Eſtate either Eccleſiaſtical or Temporal ſoever they be, ſo as no other Forreign Power ſhall or ought to have any Superiority over them; and if any perſon, that hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any other ſenſe of the Form of the ſaid Oath, ſhall accept the ſame Oath with this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, her Majeſty is well pleaſed to accept every ſuch in that behalf, as her good &amp; obedient Subjects, &amp; ſhall acquit them of all manner of Penalties contained in the ſaid Act, againſt ſuch as ſhall peremtorily or obſtinately Refuſe to take the ſaid Oath.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>And in the fifth year of her Majeſties Raign, there was an Act of Parliament to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this Senſe of the ſaid Oath, in theſe following words.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Provided alſo, That the Oath expreſſed in the ſaid Act made in the ſaid firſt year, ſhall be taken and expounded in ſuch Form as is ſet forth in an Admonition Annexed to the Queens Majeſties Injunctions, publiſhed in the firſt year of her Majeſties Raign, That is to ſay, to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61106:11"/>confeſs and acknowledg in her Majeſty, her Heirs and Succeſſors, none other Authority then that was challenged and lately uſed by the Noble King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth, and King</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>the Sixth, as in the ſaid Admonition more plainly may appear.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Now from the aforeſaid Oath, together with the aforeſaid Expoſition Confirmed by Act of Parliament: Let theſe things be Conſidered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A Solemn Aſſertion of the Queens Power and Authority in her own Kingdom and Dominions, in oppoſition to any Forreign Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State or Potentate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Power and Authority of the Queen in her own Realms, and other her Dominions, was over all Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, as well as over all Temporal Perſons, ſo as to be tryed by her Laws in all Matters and Cauſes they may be concerned in; that if innocent, they may be acquitted; but if guilty, they may be puniſhed by her Power and Authority, according to her Laws in her Courts of Juſtice, without Appealing to, or hoping for Relief from Forreign Juriſdiction.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And therefore let all thoſe who do Conſcienciouſly ſcruple to take either of the aforeſaid Oaths; Conſider whether they have not entertained ſuch notions and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of them, as the plain words and comon ſenſe of ſuch words will not fairly bear, and thereby expoſe themſelves to ſuch trouble, as they might lawfully eſcape, if their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were better informed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let ſuch as have power to tender and impoſe the ſaid Oaths upon perſons, Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whether the Tender of ſuch Oaths is not ſometimes done out of ſpite to the perſons before them, they knowing that they are of Scrupulons Conſciences, and ſo are ſure, that they have an opportunity to afflict them; and yet know in their own Conſciences that ſuch perſons are good Proteſtants, and have long lived in all peaceable manner un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Government, and ſo deſire to abide, that they may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all Godlineſs and Honeſty under Authority, as they are taught by the Good Word of God.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Another Law by which the Proteſtant Diſſenters have been and ſtill are Proſecuted and Diſtreſſed, is, the 17. of <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>viz. An Act for Reſtraining Nonconformiſts from Inhabiting Incorporations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the Perſons puniſhable by this Act, are ſuch as are Nonconformiſt Preachers, who live in a Corporation, or within five Miles of a Corporation, and that Preach in Conventicles, and thereby under pretence of Religion do diſtill Poyſonous Principles of Schiſm and Rebellion into the Hearts of his Majeſties Subjects, to the great danger of the Church and Kingdom. See the firſt Paragraph of the ſaid Statute. And the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment provided by the ſaid Statute for ſuch perſons, is the forfeiture of Forty Pounds, to be ſued for in any Court of Record at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> or before the Judges of Aſſize, and alſo ſix Months Impriſonment, if ſuch perſons ſhall Refuſe to take the Oath Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided by this Act: A Copy whereof is as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>Do Swear, that it is not lawful upon any pretence whatſoever, to take Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, and that I do abhor that Traiterous Poſition of taking Arms by his Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty against his Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Commiſſioned by him, in purſuance of ſuch Commiſſions; and that I will not at any time endeavour any Alteration of Government either in Church or State.</hi>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now from the aforeſaid Statute, Let theſe things be Conſidered.</head>
               <p n="1">1. That the Main Deſign of the ſaid Act was to rid Cities and Corporations of ſuch Nonconformiſt Miniſters, as under pretence of Religion, do diſtill Poyſonous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Schiſm and Rebellion into the Hearts of his Majeſties Subjects, to the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Church and State.</p>
               <p>Now if there be any ſuch Criminal Perſons under the name of Nonconformiſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, let them ſuffer according to their Crimes, when proved by ſufficient Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider that all ſorts of Nonconformiſt Miniſters do abhor to be ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61106:11"/>and to promote Rebellion; but they do generally make it their buſineſs to Preach Eternal Salvation by the Bleſſed Merits of Jeſus Chriſt, and a Holy Converſation, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Bleſſed Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt; following the things which make for Peace here, and hoping to injoy a Better Peace when this Life is ended.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider, That though theſe good things are managed in Separate Congregations diſtinct from the National Church, yet they ought not to be counted the Managers of Schiſm and Rebellion, but the Promoters of the Proteſtant Religion in higher degrees of Reformation, according to the Word of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſider, That for ſuch men to be expoſed to live five miles from Cities and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, or elſe to live in a Goal, ſeemeth to be hard dealing; thus being compelled to live at ſuch a diſtance from the chief places of the Kingdom, is a kind of Baniſhment from our Country, while in our Countrey, and all this for Nonconformity to the Church, and for not ſwearing all the particulars in the Oath provided by the ſaid Act; one particular being this, <hi>That I will not anytime endeavour any Alteration of Government either in Church or State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which words doth at leaſt ſuppoſe, that all things in the Church Government, are ſo well and ſo compleat, that there ought to be no endeavours to alter or amend them, and this is a great ſcruple to many perſons that are good Proteſtants.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. Another Statute by which the Proteſtant Diſſenters are Diſtreſſed, is the 22d. of <hi>Car.</hi> 2. Chap. 1. Intituled, <hi>An Act to Surpreſs Seditious Conventicles,</hi> from which Statute let theſe particular things be ſoberly conſidered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That this Statute was provided, as a further and more ſpeedy Remedy againſt the growing and dangerous Practices of Seditious Sectaries, and other Diſloyal Perſons, who under pretence of Tender Conſciences, have or may at their Meetings contrive Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections (as late Experience hath ſhewn.) <hi>See Paragraph</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Now it is well known throughout this Kingdom, that the Proteſtant Diſſenters, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven every ſort of them, do abhor to be ſuch Perſons; and therefore do deem it a great wrong, that they ſhould be accounted and proſecuted as ſuch perſons: 1. Becauſe though they be ſeparate from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> yet that doth not demonſtrate them to be Seditious Sectaries, foraſmuch as the main things in the Chriſtian Religion, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is Profeſſed by the Diſſenters, with a greater care to live ſuitably unto ſuch a Holy Profeſſion, then the generality of the Viſible Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> do make Conſcience of, and therefore they deſerve to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſuch as further the Proteſtant Reformation, and not ſuch as are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Sedition. 2. They deem it a wrong to be counted perſons of Diſloualty meerly becauſe of their Nonconformity, eſpecially conſidering what a demonſtration they have given of being peaceable under the Government for ſo many years, notwithſtanding many and great Troubles they have met with in moſt parts of this Kingdom, meerly for Matters of Conſcience, 3. And foraſmuch as mention is made of Meeting under colour and pretence of the Exerciſe of Religion, to contrive Inſurrections, the Proteſtant Diſſenters, in general, can comfortably Appeal to God and the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that they are not guilty in this Matter; and beſides this, it is not conſiſtent with good reaſon, that contriving of Inſurrections could be at all managed in the Diſſenters Meetings, foraſmuch as all ſorts of perſons do Reſort unto them, <hi>viz.</hi> Rich and Poor, young and old, and do daily find no other Matters, but the Real Exerciſe of Religion, in Praying to God, Praiſing of God, and Preaching the Word of God, that they may further the Converſion and Salvation of each other. Furthermore it is to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that ſince the making of the aforeſaid Act, and the violent Proſecution thereof, to the very great dammage of many Proteſtant Families, His Majeſty did take ſuch Grievances of his Subjects of Tender Conſciences, into his Princely and Compaſſionate Conſideration, and did Declare his Diſlike of ſuch forceable courſes in matters of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: See His Majeſties Declaration to all his Loving Subjects, <hi>March</hi> 15. 1672. Publiſhed by the Advice of his Privy Council.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Perſons in the aforeſaid Act, who are accounted Offenders, are, <hi>All ſuch who being of the Age of Sixteen years or upwards, being Subjects of this Realm, who ſhall be preſent at any Aſſembly, Conventicle or Meeting, under colour or pretence of any Exerciſe of Religion, in other manner then according to the Liturgy and Practice of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>they being in number five, or more beſides the Family or Houſhold, and if it be in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61106:12"/>a place where there is no Family Inhabiting, then the number of five or more are deemed Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now from this part of the Act, conſider that the Perſons Accounted Offenders, are ſuch whoſe Exerciſe of Religion is in other manner than according to the Liturgy and Practice of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> And therefore it is needful ſoberly to inquire, whether the Exerciſe of Religion, as it is among the Proteſtant Diſſenters, be in other manner then according to the Liturgy and Practice of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> And therefore let the Exerciſe of Religion in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and as it is among the Proteſtant Diſſenters, be well conſidered and compared together, and then we ſhall ſee whether it be Contradictious or Harmonious.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Exerciſe of Religion in the Liturgy, and as it is Practiced in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> reſpecting the matters of it, doth conſiſt of Prayers to Almighty God, in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt his only Son for Spiritual and Temporal Bleſſings; and this is the Practice of the Proteſtant Diſſenters in their Meetings.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Exerciſe of Religion, do give Thanks to God for Mercies Received from God as the Gracious Act of his Bounty and Good-Will unto ſuch as are unworthy of the leaſt Mercy; and thus do the Proteſtant Diſſenters in their Meetings.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Church of <hi>England</hi> does inſtruct Souls from the holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament, <hi>viz.</hi> From the Law and the Prophets, and from the Epiſtles and Goſpels, which doth contain the Doctrine and Practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; and thus do the Proteſtant Diſſenters, for which they are Proſecuted to their great dammage.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Church of <hi>England</hi> doth perform Religious Worſhip in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſo do the Proteſtant Diſſenters, that all Parties which come to attend the Exerciſe of Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, may underſtand what they are about.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Church of <hi>England</hi> doth obſerve the firſt day of the week, commonly called the Lords day, in Prayers and Sermons; and ſo do the Proteſtant Diſſenters; yea in this matter the Diſſenters are more careful that the day may be Religiouſly obſerved, then the Church-Proteſtants.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Proteſtant Diſſenters do agree in the Articles of Faith, reſpecting the main and ſubſtantial matters of the Proteſtant Religion; briefly thus. 1. That there is a Holy Trinity, <hi>viz.</hi> Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt. 2. That Jeſus Chriſt is very God as well as very Man, and that the Perſon of Chriſt conſidered as God and Man together, with his compleat keeping of Gods Holy Law without any Breach of it in his own Perſon, and his ſuffering the ſeverity of Divine Juſtice in the room of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, is thereby the compleat and only Saviour of all thoſe that truly Believe in him, and Repent of their Sins. 3. That the ſame Jeſus Chriſt which was Born of the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> being conceived of the Holy Ghoſt, and that dyed upon the Croſs, and after being Buried was Raiſed from the Dead, <hi>is alſo aſcended to the Right-hand of God in Heaven, there to appear in the Preſence of god, as an Advocate and Interceſſor for all them that come to God by him, and he is able to ſave them to the utmoſt.</hi> 4. Both Parties do believe that the Holy Scriptures are the Rule of Faith and Practice. 5. As concerning the Church of God upon Earth, the Diſſenters do agree with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in that deſcription gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Chriſts Viſible Church. See the Nineteenth Article of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in theſe very words: <hi>The Viſible Church of Chriſt, is a Congregation of faithful men, in which the Word of God is Preached, and Sacraments be duly Miniſtred according to Chriſts Ordinance, in all thoſe things that of Neceſſity are Requiſite to the ſame:</hi> So profeſs and confeſs the Diſſenters alſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider the puniſhments provided by the aforeſaid Statute, to be inflicted upon the Offenders, <hi>viz.</hi> five ſhillings for the firſt Offence, and ten ſhillings for the ſecond of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, for being only in the capacity of a Hearer; and Twenty Pounds for every houſe that ſhall entertain any ſuch Conventicle, and Twenty Pounds for the firſt Offence of him that ſhall Teach or Preach in ſuch Meetings, and Forty Pounds for every ſuch Offence after the firſt Conviction; and alſo Power in given to the Juſtices of Peace, to Levy the Fines of ſome perſons upon others, ſo far as Ten Pounds and all theſe Fines to be levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Goods and Chattles of the Offenders.</p>
               <p>And in the Proſecuting of many Perſons by the aforeſaid Statute, much more then the Sums of Money Levyed have been taken away, and the Goods Sold without making any Return of the over-pluſs, to the very great dammage of many good Proteſtant Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:61106:12"/>
               <p>And now whether ſuch Proceedings be the beſt way to ſurpreſs Popery and promote the Proteſtant Religion, ſhall be left to the ſerious conſideration of all ſorts of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, eſpecially to Proteſtant Magiſtrates, who oftentimes have opportunity to diſplay Juſtice with Wiſdom and Mercy, which is far better then ſuch Severity as looketh too much like Cruelty. And therefore as a help to ſuch Magiſtrates as are perplexed with Informers by the demand of Warrants to diſturb Peaceable Proteſtants in their Meetings, and in the Seizure of their Goods afterward, let theſe following things be inquired into by ſuch Magiſtrates as deſire to diſcharge their Office faithfully in doing Juſtice between the King and the Subject.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether all the People above the number of five beſides the Family, are the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this Realm; for they are the Offenders in the ſenſe of this Statute, and not the Subjects of other Realms, and therefore the Informer ought to ſwear that thoſe he doth inform againſt, are Subjects of this Realm.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether there was any endeavours to make or contrive any Inſurrections againſt the Government; for the very deſign of the aforeſaid Act was to prevent ſuch Meetings.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether there was any ſeditious words ſpoken in the Prayers or Preaching of the Aſſembly of People, ſeeing this Act was made on purpoſe to ſuppreſs Seditious Meetings.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether the Praying and Preaching was according to the Liturgy and Practice of the Church of <hi>England, viz.</hi> whether the Prayers were Proteſtant Prayers, and the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proteſtant Preaching, ſo as to promote the Proteſtant Religion, or ſome other Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; if the Informers ſhould ſay they were not there long enough to know the truth of theſe things, then it will be evident that ſuch men are not fit to be ſworn Evidences againſt ſuch Meetings, forasmuch as their Oath doth not reach to ſuch matters of Fact as is mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Statute.</p>
               <p>And theſe things ought to be the more narrowly looked into, becauſe thoſe that turn Informers are uſually ſuch as have ſome particular ſpite againſt ſome particular perſons, and ſo inſtead of doing Juſtice according to Law, do but ſeek after ſome Revenge for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the Perſons of ſuch as they are offended at; or elſe it is done that they may have that wages mentioned in the Act, <hi>viz.</hi> the third part of the Fines of ſuch perſons they ſwear againſt, and ſo ſtrive to make themſelves rich by making others poor.</p>
               <p>And this is to be greatly lamented, that ſome Juſtices of the Peace have mightily fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered the Informers, by being too ready to receive their Informations and by Convicting Perſons of divers Offences, as they called them before ever the perſon knew of ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction; and ſo ſending divers Warrants of diſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs altogether, amounting to very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſums of Money. A Hot-headed Conſtable preſently becomes a Slave to the proud In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, and ſo maketh a ſuddain Seizure upon the outward Subſtance of ſuch as fear God and love Godlineſs. and whereas the Juſtices may, if they will, lay but the Fine of Five Shillings upon a perſon for his firſt, or ten ſhillings for his ſecond Offence, they do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times lay the ſum of ten pounds for the defaults of others, and ſo add many ten pounds together to the near Ruining of ſome perſons. <hi>And thus they that depart from evil maketh themſelves a Prey, but the Lord will ſee and ſhow himſelf diſpleaſed at it.</hi> See Iſaiah 59.15.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Another way of diſtreſing and perplexing the Poor Proteſtant Diſſenters, is by the Proceedings of the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, the ways and methods of whoſe Proceedings are as followeth:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſaid Eccleſiaſtical Courts do require the Church-Wardens and Miniſters to make Preſentment of ſuch perſons as do not come to their Pariſh-Church, and unto the Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Upon Receiving ſuch Preſentments, then the ſaid Courts do iſſue forth Citations for ſuch Perſons being Preſented to come and make anſwer to the ſaid Preſentments.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the ſaid Citations be not ſerved upon the perſons who are Preſented, then the ſaid Courts cauſe a Paper called <hi>Viis &amp; Modis</hi> to be ſet upon the Church-Door, or upon the Perſons own Door, requiring the Perſon to appear upon a certain day.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If the Perſon do not appear, then the ſaid Court proceedeth to Excommunication for Contempt.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If the Perſon do appear, then the Court doth acquaint ſuch Perſon that he is Preſented for not coming to Church, and for not Receiving the Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If the Perſon do not make it appear that he hath been at Church, and taken the Sacrament within the time mentioned in the ſaid Preſentment, then the Judge of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61106:13"/>ſaid Court doth proceed to Admonition, That the ſaid Perſon ſhall Repair to his Pariſh Church, and take the Sacrament by ſuch a day as is appointed by the Admonition, and bring a Certificate from the Miniſter of the ſaid Pariſh, that he hath ſo done, whether fit for it or no.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If the ſaid Perſon do not obey the ſaid Admonition then the Eccleſiaſtical Court does Decre him Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, and ſo ſend an Excommunication to the Miniſter, requiring him to publiſh the ſame upon ſuch Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day or Holy-day as they appoint.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If the ſaid perſon ſtand Excommunicated forty days, then the Biſhop of the Dioceſs doth Certify this matter in the High-Court of Chancery, by a certain thing called a <hi>Significavit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Then the High-Court of Chancery in the Term-time, doth award forth or grant a Writ called <hi>De Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicato Capiendo,</hi> which is directed to the Sheriffs of the City or County where the Excommunicate Perſon is an Inhabitant, that the ſaid Perſon may be Apprehended and Committed to Priſon, and there to remain without Bail or Mainprize, until he ſhall ſatisfy the Church-Party, ſo as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Abſolution; which may be obtained ſeveral wayes, as it is allowed and practiſed by the Eccleſiaſtical <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Firſt by ſwearing the Eccleſiaſtical Oath, which is to ſwear to obey all the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Laws, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Lawful Commands of his Ordinary; Secondly giving a Bond to Conform upon the Penalty of ſo much money as ſhall be agreed upon between the Excommunicated Perſon and the aforeſaid Court, which formerly uſed to be ten pounds, but now of late years the Eccleſiaſtical Market is riſen, and twenty pounds Bond is required; Thirdly, ſuch as are not willing to take the aforeſaid Oath, nor give the aforeſaid Bond, may be abſolved, and ſo allowed ſome time to Conform, if they will pay a Pledge, which uſually is ten pounds preſent payment; and he that will not comply with any of theſe ways, muſt abide in Goal, whatever becometh of his poor Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; and beſides all this the ſaid perſon muſt pay the Charges of the Eccleſiaſtical Court, which is ſometimes ordinary, and ſometimes extraordinary; the ordinary charges is about Forty Shillings.</p>
               <p>And now that it may be demonſtrated, that the Proteſtant Diſſenters are not obſtinate, but Conſcienci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in their Nonconformity to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> let theſe Cauſes and Reaſons of their Nonconformity be ſoberly conſiderd in the particulars following:</p>
               <p>The Proteſtant Diſſenters cannot Conform to the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe they cannot find a National Church in the New Teſtament, But the Churches they find there are Congregational Churches, which conſiſted of ſuch Perſons as God by his Word and Spirit had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from a State of Nature to a State of Grace. Such were the Churches of <hi>Jeruſalem, Samaria, Antioch, Corinth,</hi> and <hi>Epheſus, &amp;c.</hi> who being perſons ſeparated from the people amongſt whom they were Inhabitants, did by a mutual Conſent and Agreement one with another. maintain a Holy Communion together in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, as it was ſounded upon the Word of God: And ſo they were the Nonconformiſts of that day, and underwent great Sufferings for not Conforming to that Worſhip which was Eſtabliſhed in the places where they inhabited.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe they cannot find any ſuch Officers belonging to a Church of Chriſt in the New-Teſtament, as Arch-biſhops Lord Biſhops Deans, Arch-Deacons, Prebends, Commiſſaries, Officials, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But they find ſuch Offiers in the Church of Chriſt as are called Paſtors, Eldery, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>d Overſeers, and the word Biſhop doth belong to the ſame perſons under the former Title, conſidered as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeders of, and Rulers over the true Church of Chriſt; and the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> doth forbid the Biſhops of Chriſts Church to be Lords over Gods Heritage, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Proteſtant Diſſenters cannot Conform to the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Holy Sacrament, called in Scripture the Lords Supper, becauſe that Holy Ordinance is not Adminiſtred unto the Communicants as Converted Perſons, but as thoſe who by Tradition are brought up to Acknowledge and Confeſs Chriſt, although in works too many deny him by living Prophane Lives, being greatly guilty of Swearing, Curſing and Drunkenneſs, and divers other ſcandalous matters; which is a Reproach to the Proteſtant Religion; for although the Proteſtant Religion be the Reformed Religion, yet thouſands of thoſe that profeſs it are not Reformed Perſons; and beſides this too many of thoſe who are Miniſters of the ſaid Church, and ſo are Adminiſtrators of this Holy Ordinance are known to be very unholy in their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, notwithſtanding all which, the Proteſtant Diſſenters have a great veneration and high eſteem of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny both of the Nobility, Gentry, Clergy, and Common People, of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who live ſober lives, and walk Conſcienciouſly in Civil and Religious Matters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Several other Reaſons might be added, but theſe ſhall ſuffice for the preſent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now foraſmuch as the Proteſtant Religion is Profeſs'd by his Majesties Subjects in general, conſidered as Conformists and Nonconformiſts, and both Parties are agreed in the main and ſubſtantial parts thereof, and alſo both Parties are in a like danger of the Papiſts; If ever the Government of this Realm ſhould fall into their hands, (which God of his Infinite Mercy prevent, for then the Church-Proteſtants as well as the Diſſenting Proteſtants would be deemed Fanaticks, Schismaticks, Hereticks yea, Rebelis, and would be Proſecuted as ſuch) Therefore it highly concerns all ſorts of Proteſtants to ſay to one another, as</hi> Abraham <hi>to</hi> Lot, Gen. 13.7, 8. Let there be no ſtrife between us, for we are Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: <hi>Eſpecially conſidering the Popiſh</hi> Canaanite <hi>and</hi> Perizite <hi>are now too much in our Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. Therefore all things whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
